Sebastien VARRETTE, PhD

Research Scientist, Deputy Head HPC for Research Management, Security and Performance of HPC systems

Phone: +33(0)6 74 57 90 05 E-mail: Sebastien.Varrette@uni.lu Home page: http://varrette.gforge.uni.lu GPG Key ID: 5D08BCDD4F156AD7



Born on November 27th, 1979 (in France) Married (2004), two children (2007,2010)

Short bio: With more than 13 years of postdoctoral and team management experience, Dr. Varrette is Research Scientist within the University of Luxembourg. Expert in the deployment and management of High Performance Computing (HPC) systems, he is leading with Prof. Pascal Bouvry the development of the University's HPC and Big Data platform, as well as the associated core expert team managing and supporting it.

In parallel, he is pursuing his research in the domains of the security and performance of parallel and distributed computing platforms, such as HPC, Cloud Computing or Data Analytics infrastructures. His research contributions led to more than 80 publications in high-level scientific journals, or international conference proceedings while co-authoring 4 books. He has a strong involvement in the community with reviewing roles in impact journals, conferences organization (e.g., IEEE CloudCom) and the participation to more than 50 conference program committee.

Finally, he takes part for the management committee and represents Luxembourg within multiple EU HPC projects, such as PRACE (acting Advisor), ETP4HPC or several COST actions. He has also concrete contributions in several strategic projects linked to HPC developed with multiple key decision makers in the Luxembourg context, either from the private sector or at the governmental level. He's also acting as HPC expert for the European Commission in the Enhanced Regional EU-ASEAN Dialogue Instrument (E-READI) program.

TECHNICAL / MANAGEMENT High Performance Computing (HPC), Big Data (BD) & Cloud technologies.

EXPERTISE: Managing large-scale HPC and Data analytics systems since 2003 (Linux environment)

HPC Team Leader since 2007 (Deputy head, HPC for Research)

MAIN RESEARCH DOMAINS: Security and Evaluation of Distributed Computing Platforms

Education

| 2007 | Ph.D. In Computer Science, University of Luxembourg (UL) & Institut National Thesis: Security in Large Scale Distributed System | • |
|------|---|---|
| 2003 | M.Sc. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE (Univ. de Grenoble, | · |
| | Speciality: Cryptology, Security and Information (| Coding (CSCI), rank: 1st |
| 2003 | Master's Degree in Engineering (Telecoms EN | SIMAG, Grenoble) with honours $(B/2.1)$ |
| | Speciality: Applied Mathematics, Computer Scien | ces & Telecommunications rank: top 10% |

Employment

| 2007 - now | Research Scientist (UL, Luxembourg) |
|-------------|--|
| 2004 - 2007 | Research Assistant (UL, Luxembourg) |
| 2003 | IT (LAB) AND HPC SYSTEM MANAGER (ID-IMAG, Grenoble, France). |

Awards

| 2018 | Best Paper Award, 32 th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Information Networking (ICoin 2018) |
|------|--|
| 2014 | Best Student Paper Award, 8 th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Network & System Security (NSS 2014) |

Teaching Experience

| 2019 | Data Sciences Training for European Commission employees (Digital Pole) | | |
|-------------|---|---------------------------------------|--|
| 2014 - now | UL HPC Schools | https://hpc.uni.lu/hpc-school/ | |
| 2008 - now | Parallel & Grid Computing | Master MICS2 (UL) | |
| 2004 - 2007 | Programming Techniques I | Bachelor I1/CUT1 (UL) | |
| | Advanced Programming in C, C++ and Java | Bachelor I2 (UL) | |
| | System Administration and Network Security | Master CSCI2 (UJF) | |
| 2006 | CRYPTOLOGY AND NETWORK SECURITY | Master (Univ. of Yaoundé I, Cameroon) | |

Graduate Students Supervision

| PostDocs. | EZHILMATHI KRISHNASAMY (2019 –) PRACE-6IP project coordination, advanced HPC/research support |
|------------------|---|
| | EMMANUEL KIEFFER (2019 –) Bi-level optimization and scalable science |
| | ALBAN ROUSSET $(2016-2018)$ Large scale parallel simulation for Discrete Element Method |
| | Joseph Emeras $(2014-2016)$ Workload Analysis and Characterization of HPC Platforms for the Study of |
| | Virtualization Service |
| PhD. | LUDOVICA PASERI (2019 –) GDPR compliance in Eurorean HPC and Cloud Computing Initiatives |
| | ABDALLAH A.Z.A. IBRAHIM $(2017-2020)$ Presence: Toward a Novel Approach for Performance Evaluation |
| | of Mobile Cloud SaaS Web Services |
| | ABDOUL-WAHID C. MAINASSARA (2017 –) Large scale parallel simulation for Discrete Element Method |
| | Chao Liu (2017 –) Pricing strategies for cloud brokers at the Software-as-a-Service (SaaS) level |
| | Jakub Muszyński $(2011-2015)$ Cheating-Tolerance of Parallel and Distributed Evolutionary Algorithms in |
| | Desktop Grids and Volunteer Computing Systems |
| | BENOÎT BERTHOLON (2010 – 2013) CertiCloud & JShadObf: Toward Integrity and Software Protection in |
| | Cloud Computing Platforms |
| $In \ addition:$ | 22 master and 5 bachelor students supervision for their last year project and training. |
| | Team leader (deputy head), Core management team of the Uni.lu HPC facility (Total: 8 FTEs). |

Research Projects

| 2007 - now | UL High Performance Computing (HPC), co-PI (UL cumulative contribution: 23,586,151 €) | | |
|-------------|---|--|--|
| 2019 - 2022 | EU H2020 PRACE 6th Implementation Phase Project (PRACE-6IP) | | |
| 2014 - 2018 | EU COST ACTION IC1305: Network for Sustainable Ultrascale Computing (NESUS) | | |
| 2016 - 2019 | co-PI, UL LSDEM (UL contribution: 332 k€) | | |
| 2014 - 2016 | AFR PostDoc J. Emeras (Evalix; Co-Supervisor; Total/AFR contribution: 56 k€) | | |
| | Workload Analysis & Characterization of HPC Platforms for the Study of Virtualization Service | | |
| 2011 - 2013 | UL EvoPerf (UL contribution: 373 k€) | | |
| 2010 - 2012 | FNR CORE GreenIT (Total: 1,5 M€, FNR contribution: 432 k€) | | |
| 2010 - 2012 | AFR PhD B. Bertholon (PHD-09-142; Scientific Advisor; Total/AFR contribution: 110 k€) | | |
| | Confidentiality and Integrity Issues over Cloud Computing Platforms | | |
| 2009 - 2013 | EU COST ACTION IC0804: Energy efficiency in large scale distributed systems, EU COREGRID | | |
| Before 2008 | ANR SAFESCALE-BGPR, GRID'5000 (technical committee), FNR-SECOM TESEGRAD, | | |
| | CRYPTALPES, RAGTIME etc. | | |

Professional Development and Recognitions

```
IEEE Computer and Computational Intelligence society member
                Autorisation à Diriger des Recherches (ADR), 2019
                Participation to Ph.D Boards: A. Rousset (2016), G. Pozetti (2018), D. Guyon (2018)
                Various editorial responsibilities
                    Reviewer for International Projects: National Science Center (Poland)
                    Reviewer for several impact journals and international (IEEE, ACM) conferences
                    Member of more than 50 international Technical Program Committee,
                    Organizer of various conferences, either as general, program or track chair
                UL HPC Manager (Deputy head) and Team leader since 2007.
                    Cumulative Project Investment: 23,586,151 € (as of 2020).
                   552 computing nodes (110 servers), 46896 cores, 96GPU accelerators, R_{\text{peak}} = 2794.23 TFlops
                    Shared Storage capacity: 10713.4 TB, over NFS, GPFS/Spectrumscale, Lustre File Systems
2019 - 2020
                EC HPC expert, Enhanced Regional EU-ASEAN Dialogue Instrument (E-READI) program
2019 - now
                Advisory board member, Luxembourg Joint Artificial Intelligence (AI) Lab with NVidia
2017 - now
                PRACE Management committee: Luxembourg representative (acting advisor)
                    Partnership for Advanced Computing in Europe
                Management committee member within ETP4HPC
2016 - now
                    European Technology Platform (ETP) in the area of High-Performance Computing (HPC)
2018 - now
                National ICT standardization delegate: ISO/TC 307: Blockchain and DLTs
2016
                General Chair, 8th IEEE Intl. Conf. Cloud Computing Technology & Science (CloudCom'16)
                Delegate representing Luxembourg in EU COST Actions IC1305 and IC0804
2009 - 2018
                HPC Technical advisor for Luxembourg' MECO and SMC Ministries on HPC projects
2009 - now
                Manager of various complementary Research Computing / IT services
2007 - now
2006
                EGIDE mission for 3 weeks in Cameroon (master lecture – Univ. of Yaoudé I)
```

| Publication category | Quantity |
|--|----------|
| Books | 7 |
| Magazine | 1 |
| Book Chapters | 12 |
| Edited Books / Proceedings | 1 |
| International journals | 9 |
| International conferences with proceedings and reviews | 52 |
| (French) national conferences with proceedings and reviews | 4 |
| International conferences with reviews (no proceedings) | 7 |
| PhD Thesis | 1 |
| Masters Thesis | 1 |
| Technical Reports and Presentations | 39 |
| Miscellaneous / Poster | 1 |
| Total: | 135 |

| Publish | Papers:177 | Citations:823, Years:17 | h-index:13 | g-index:25 |
|--------------------|-------------------|-------------------------|---------------------|------------------------|
| or Perish | Cites/year: 48.41 | Cites/paper: 4.65 | Authors/paper: 3.75 | Query date: 2020-07-22 |
| Orbi ^{lu} | DBLP | Google Scholar | | |

Selected Publications

- [1] J.-G. Dumas, P. Lafourcade, A. Tichit, and S. Varrette. Les blockchains en 50 questions: comprendre le fonctionnement et les enjeux de cette technologie innovante. Dunod, 2nd edition, November 2019. 296 pages, in French.
- [2] J.-G. Dumas, J.-L. Roch, E. Tannier, and S. Varrette. *Théorie des Codes : Compression, Cryptage et Correction*. Collection Sciences Sup. Dunod, 3rd edition, August 2018. 384 pages, in French.
- [3] J.-G. Dumas, J.-L. Roch, E. Tannier, and S. Varrette. Foundations of Coding: Compression, Encryption, Error-Correction. Wiley & Sons, February 2015. 376 pages.
- [4] S. Varrette and N. Bernard. *Programmation avancée en C (avec exercices et corrigés)*. Collection Informatique et Systèmes d'Informations. Hermès, Fev. 2007. 416 pages, in French.
- [5] J. Emeras, S. Varrette, V. Plugaru, and P. Bouvry. Amazon elastic compute cloud (ec2) versus in-house hpc platform: A cost analysis. *IEEE Trans. Cloud Computing*, 7(2):456–468, April 2019.
- [6] A. A. Z. A. Ibrahim, M. U. Wasim, S. Varrette, and Pascal Bouvry. PRESENCE: Monitoring and Modelling the Performance Metrics of Mobile Cloud SaaS Web Services. J. Mobile Information Systems, 2018(1351386), August 2018. Extended journal version of IEEE ICoin 2018 best paper paper.
- [7] M. Guzek, S. Varrette, V. Plugaru, J. E. Pecero, and P. Bouvry. A Holistic Model of the Performance and the Energy-Efficiency of Hypervisors in an HPC Environment. *Intl. J. on Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience (CCPE)*, 26(15):2569–2590, October 2014.
- [8] J. Muszyński, S. Varrette, P. Bouvry, F. Seredyński, and S. U. Khan. Convergence Analysis of Evolutionary Algorithms in the Presence of Crash-Faults and Cheaters. *Intl. Journal. of Computers and Mathematics with Applications* (CAMWA), 64(12):3805–3819, December 2012.
- [9] S. Varrette, F. Pinel, E. Kieffer, G. Danoy, and P. Bouvry. Automatic Software Tuning of Parallel Programs for Energy-Aware Executions. In Proc. of 13th Intl. Conf. on Parallel Processing and Applied Mathematics (PPAM 2019), LNCS, Bialystok, Poland, 2019. Springer Verlag. Publication expected to appear in 2020.
- [10] A. A.Z.A. Ibrahim, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. PRESENCE: Toward a Novel Approach for Performance Evaluation of Mobile Cloud SaaS Web Services. In *Proc. of the 32nd IEEE Intl. Conf. on Information Networking (ICOIN 2018)*, pages 50–55, Chiang Mai, Thailand, January 2018. IEEE Computer Society. **Best Paper Award**.
- [11] J. Muszyński, S. Varrette, J.L. Jiménez Laredo, and P. Bouvry. Exploiting the Hard-wired Vulnerabilities of Newscast via Connectivity-splitting Attack. In *Proc. of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Network and System Security (NSS 2014)*, volume 8792 of *LNCS*, pages 152–165, Xi'an, China, October 2014. Springer Verlag. **Best Student Paper Award**.
- [12] B. Bertholon, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. CertiCloud: a Novel TPM-based Approach to Ensure Cloud IaaS Security. In *Proc. of the 4th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Cloud Computing (CLOUD 2011)*, Washington DC, USA, July 2011. IEEE Computer Society.